Finding Aid for Rudy Serra Papers, 1983-1984 and 1991-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rudy Serra papers 1983-1984 and 1991-2002
Serra, Rudy
1.5 linear feet.
0595 Aa 2
The papers of Rudy Serra are concentrated on his involvement and interest in the revision of city ordinances in Ferndale and Ypsilanti, Michigan, widening the scope of civil rights protection to include sexual orientation. The collection includes his writings in support of ordinance revision, an article he wrote on sexual orientation and Michigan law, as well as correspondence related to, and press coverage of, the revision process.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Judge Serra (donor no. 9597 ) in 2005 and 2008.
The collection is open to research.
Rudolph A. Serra earned his master's degree at Central Michigan University and his JD at Wayne State University. He served as a research attorney for the Michigan Court of Appeals, was a Ferndale School Board member and Oakland County Commissioner. He was president of the Stonewall Bar Association which assists legal professionals with an interest in sexual orientation issues and the law as it relates to gay, lesbian and bisexual people. Serra served as an attorney, counselor, and social worker through his firm Rudolph A. Serra, P.C., specializing in criminal defense, civil rights, health law, mental health, and consumer litigation. Serra was also a licensed social worker with guardian ad litem and other litigation-support experience. Serra served as a Michigan Democratic Party Officer at Large, chair of the MDP's Gay/Lesbian Caucus and co-chair of the MDP's Justice Caucus. Serra was an alternate delegate to the 2000 Democratic National Convention.
Rudy Serra was appointed as Judge of the 36th District Court in Detroit in 2004 by Governor Granholm.
The collection is comprised of four series: Ferndale Civil Rights Ordinance Revision; Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality; Other Litigation; Topical Files; and Writings.
Subjects:
Serra, Rudy.; Ferndale (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Gays--Legal status, laws, etc.--Michigan--Ferndale.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Gays--Legal status, laws, etc.--Michigan--Ypsilanti.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Ferndale Civil Rights Ordinance Revision, 1991
  The Ferndale Civil Rights Ordinance Revision series includes Judge Serra's writings about the ordinance, notably an article for the Michigan State Bar entitled "Sexual Orientation and Michigan Law." Other files include correspondence about the ordinance revisions, along with copies of the proposed ordinance revisions. Clippings from local newspapers covering the story are combined with miscellaneous records. A videotape of a Ferndale City Council meeting in 1991 features Serra's appearance as well as other public statements both for and against revisions.
  - Civil Rights Ordinance (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Press and Informational, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes regarding ordinance (Box 1)
  - VHS Videotape - Ferndale City Council, July 22, 1991 (Box 1)
    (The first five minutes of tape are of a TV movie, Council coverage begins after 5 minutes, Mr. Serra appears for three minutes at approximately 30 minutes into the tape, coverage continues with further discussion of proposed amendments)
- Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality, 2002
  The Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality series contains copies of court documents pertaining to a ballot proposal that, if passed, would have nullified certain Ypsilanti city ordinances. These ordinances were originally enacted to protect the civil rights of gays and lesbians in Ypsilanti. The ballot proposal was defeated in the election of November 2002.
  - Plaintiffs' Response and First Amendment Complaint (Box 1)
  - Plaintiffs' Supp. Brief on Remand, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Plaintiffs' Answer to Motion (draft) (Box 1)
  - Plaintiffs' Supp. Brief Reg. Scope of Prop. Amendment (Box 1)
  - Application of Intervenor Defendant, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Plaintiffs' Response Brief (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous briefs, 1 expandable folder (Box 1)
- Other litigation
  - City of Detroit v. Sukhpreet Singh Garcha (Box 1)
    (Serra as judge ruled that defendant, an adherent of the Sikh religion, could wear his Kirpan, an ornamental knife)
  - Durhal v. Engler, 2002 (Box 1)
    (Rudy Serra was lead counsel in action to force Governor Engler to call a special election in a vacant State House seat for Detroit; election was called and Fred Durhal was elected)
  - Transgender case (not identified by name) (Box 2)
  - Triangle Foundation et al v. State Representative Deborah Whyman, 1998 (Box 2)
    (plaintiff had claimed that the Triangle Foundation "has proclaimed its support of sex acts between grown men and boys")
- Topical files
  - Awards and personal (Box 2)
  - Campaign for Wayne State University Board of Governors, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Ferndale Schools (legal opinion regarding non-discrimination policy), 1995 (Box 2)
  - H.B.5000 (legislation providing protection from discrimination based on sexual orientation), 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    (letters and other materials sent to Representative James Dressel, most of the letters were from constituents opposed to the legislation)
  - International Association of Official Human Rights Agencies, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Nichols (Rudy J.), Sixth Judicial Court Judge, 1998 (Box 2)
    (correspondence regarding note in article written by Serra in which there is criticism of "sexual orientation" being eliminated from ethnic intimidation statute)
  - Oakland County (position of county regarding protection for Gays) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Writings
  - "'Bay a Fag' Operation in Michigan: Police Misconduct, Entrapment and Crimes Against Gay Men" (Box 2)
  - "Inclusion and Credibility: The Basics of Sexual Orientation" 2000 (Box 2)
  - "Sexual Orientation and Michigan Law" 1997 (Box 2)